=======================================
<=>	System Design PDFs 158 Pages	<=>
=======================================

1.	https://blog.bytebytego.com/p/free-system-design-pdf-158-pages

2.	System Design Blueprint: The Ultimate Guide

3.	Kubernetes Tools Ecosystem


================================================================================
<==>	1.	https://blog.bytebytego.com/p/free-system-design-pdf-158-pages	<==>
================================================================================
		
Page No :6		What is IaaS/PaaS/SaaS?
			
YM	->	You manage
PM	->	Provider manages
			
				 ---------------------------------------
				|Traditional IT	|IaaS	|PaaS	|SaaS	|
 -------------------------------------------------------
|Applications	|		YM		|	YM	|	YM	|	PM	|
 -------------------------------------------------------
|Data			|		YM		|	YM	|	YM	|	PM	|
 -------------------------------------------------------
|Runtime		|		YM		|	YM	|	PM	|   PM	|
 -------------------------------------------------------
|Middleware		|		YM		|	YM	|	PM	|	PM	|
 -------------------------------------------------------
|OS				|		YM		|	PM	|	PM	|	PM	|
 -------------------------------------------------------
|Virtualization	|		YM		|	PM	|	PM	|	PM	|
 -------------------------------------------------------
|Servers		|		YM		|	PM	|	PM	|	PM	|
 -------------------------------------------------------
|Storage		|		YM		|	PM	|	PM	|	PM	|
 -------------------------------------------------------
|Networking		|		YM		|	PM	|	PM	|	PM	|
 -------------------------------------------------------
			
Page No :8		Most popular programming languages

	Programming languages come and go. Some stand the test of time. Some already are shooting stars and some are rising rapidly on the horizon.
	
	I draw a diagram by putting the top 38 most commonly used programming languages in one place, sorted by year. Data source: StackOverflow survey.
	
	1 JavaScript 		2 HTML/CSS 			3 Python
	4 SQL				5 Java				6 Node
	7 TypeScript 		8 C					9 Bash/Shell 
	10 C				11 PHP				12 C
	13 PowerShell 		14 Go				15 Kotlin
	16 Rust				17 Ruby				18 Dart
	19 Assembly 		20 Swift			21 R
	22 VBA				23 Matlab			24 Groovy
	25 Objective-C 		26 Scala			27 Perl
	28 Haskell			29 Delphi			30 Clojure
	31 Elixir			32 LISP				33 Julia
	34 F				35 Erlang			36 APL
	37 Crystal			38 COBOL

Page No :9		What is the future of online payments?
	I don’t know the answer, but I do know one of the candidates is the blockchain.
	
Page No :11		What is SSO (Single Sign-On)?
	Basically, Single Sign-On (SSO) is an authentication scheme. It allows a user to log in to different systems using a single ID.
	
Page No :13		How to store passwords safely in the database?
	What is salt?
	According to OWASP guidelines, "a salt is a unique, randomly generated string that is added to each password as part of the hashing process".

Page No :16		How does HTTPS work?

Page No	:20		A visual guide on how to choose the right Database
	
	Data can be structured (SQL table schema), semi-structured (JSON, XML, etc.), and unstructured (Blob).

	Common database categories include: 
	
	1.	Structured
			Relational
			Columnar
	2.	Semi structured
			Key-value
			In-memory
			Wide column
			Time Series
			Immutable ledger
			Geospatial 
			Graph 
			Document 
			Text search 
	3.	Unstructured
			Blob
		
Page No :22		Do you know how to generate globally unique IDs?
	Requirements:
		Globally unique
		Roughly sorted by time
		Numerical values only
		64 bits
		Highly scalable, 
		low latency
		
Page No: 26		What is the difference between Process and Thread?

							 -------------------
							|  Program (Disk)	|
							 -------------------
 -------------------------------------------------------------------------------
|																				|
|	 	 ---				 ---				 ---				 ---		|
|		|	|				|	|				|	|				|	|		|
|	 	 ---				 ---				 ---				 ---		|
|	Image Capture.app	  iMovie.app	 IntelliJ IDEA CE.app	  Keynote.app	|
|																				|
|	 	 ---				 ---				 ---				 ---		|
|		|	|				|	|				|	|				|	|		|
|	 	 ---				 ---				 ---				 ---		|
|	  Microsoft 			Microsoft   		Microsoft		MindNode.app	|
|	  OneNote.app			Outlook.app			Word.app						|
|																				|
|	 	 ---				 ---				 ---				 ---		|
|		|	|				|	|				|	|				|	|		|
|	 	 ---				 ---				 ---				 ---		|
|	Photo Booth.app		  Photos.app		  PlayOnMac.app		Podcasts.app	|
|																				|
 -------------------------------------------------------------------------------



			 ---------------
			| Process (RAM)	|
			 ---------------
 -----------------------------------------------
|	Task Manager								|
|-----------------------------------------------|
|	File	Options		View					|
|-----------------------------------------------|
|	Processes									|
|-----------------------------------------------|
|	Name 			 |	CPU	59%	|	Memory 48%	|
|--------------------|----------|---------------|
| Firefox (7)		 |	1.5%	|	396.8 MB	|
| Google Chrome (20) |	21.2%	|	700.0 MB	|
| Microsoft Word	 |	0%		|	158.1 MB	|
| Snipping Tool		 |	2.8%	|	5.2 MB		|
| Task Manager		 |	0.4%	|	26.5 MB		|
 -----------------------------------------------

		
					   --------			--------
				 -----|	Process|	 --| Thread |
	 -------	|	  |		   |	|  |		|
	|Program|---|-----|	Process|----|  |		|
	 -------	|	  |		   |	|  |		|
	  Disk	 	 -----|	Process|	 --| Thread |
		|			   --------			--------
		|				  RAM			 Process
		|
	 --------------
	|instruction 1 |
	|--------------|
	|instruction 2 |
	|--------------|
	|...		   |
	|--------------|
	|instruction #n|
	 -------------- 

	To better understand this question, let’s first take a look at what is a Program. 
	A Program is an executable file containing a set of instructions and passively stored on disk. 
	One program can have multiple processes. For example, the Chrome browser creates a different process for every single tab.
	A Process means a program is in execution. When a program is loaded into the memory and becomes active, the program becomes a process. 
	The process requires some essential resources such as registers, program counter, and stack.
	
	A Thread is the smallest unit of execution within a process.
	The following process explains the relationship between program, process, and thread.
	
	1. The program contains a set of instructions.
	2. The program is loaded into memory. It becomes one or more running processes.
	3. When a process starts, it is assigned memory and resources. A process can have one or more threads. 
	For example, in the Microsoft Word app, a thread might be responsible for spelling checking and the other thread for inserting text into the doc.

	Main differences between process and thread:
	
	Processes are usually independent, while threads exist as subsets of a process.
	Each process has its own memory space. Threads that belong to the same process share the same memory.
	A process is a heavyweight operation. It takes more time to create and terminate.
	Context switching is more expensive between processes. Inter-thread communication is faster for threads.
	
	Over to you:
	1). Some programming languages support coroutine. What is the difference between coroutine and thread?
	2). How to list running processes in Linux?

Page No: 30		Deployment strategies

	Multi-Service Deployment
	Blue-Green Deployment
	Canary Deployment
	A/B Test
	
Page No: 35		How to design a secure web API access for your website?

	In this post, we explore two common ways:
	1. Token based authentication
	2. HMAC (Hash-based Message Authentication Code) authentication
	
Page No: 38		How do microservices collaborate and interact with each other?
	There are two ways: Orchestration and Choreography.
	
Page No: 40		What are the differences between Virtualization (VMware) and Containerization (Docker)?
	
	==================================
	Virtualization vs Containerization
	==================================

	
	|		Bare Metal		|
	|						|
	|						|
	|  ----	   ----	   ----	|
	| |App1|  |App2|  |App3||
	|-----------------------|
	|	Operating System	|
	|-----------------------|
	|	Physical Server		|
	|-----------------------|
	|		Networking		|
	 -----------------------


	
	|		Virtualized		|
	|						|
	|						|
	|----------- -----------|
	|	  VM	|	VM		|
	|----	----|	----	|
	|App1| |App2|  |App3|	|
	|-----------|-----------|
	|Guest OS	|Guest OS	|
	|-----------------------|
	| 		Hypervisor		|
	|-----------------------|
	|Host Operating System	|
	|-----------------------|
	|	Physical Server		|
	|-----------------------|
	|		Networking		|
	 -----------------------


	
	|		Containerized		  |
	|							  |
	|							  |
	|--------- --------- ---------|
	|Container|Container|Container|
	|		  | 		|		  |
	|	----  |	  ----	|	----  |
	|  |App1| |	 |App2|	|  |App3| |
	|-----------------------------|
	| 		Container Engine	  |
	|-----------------------------|
	|	Host Operating System	  |
	|-----------------------------|
	|		Physical Server		  |
	|-----------------------------|
	|			Networking		  |
	 -----------------------------



	|		Containerized on Virtualized		|
	|											|
	|----------------------- -------------------|
	|	Virtual Machine		|	Virtual Machine	|
	|----------- -----------|-------------------|
	|Container	|Container	|	Container		|
	|	 ----	|	 ----	|	   ---- 		|
	|	|App1|	|	|App2|	|	  |App3|		|
	|-----------------------|-------------------|
	|	Container Engine	|	Container Engine|
	|-----------------------|-------------------|
	|		Guest OS		|	Guest OS		|
	|-------------------------------------------|
	| 				Hypervisor					|
	|-------------------------------------------|
	|			Host Operating System			|
	|-------------------------------------------|
	|				Physical Server				|
	|-------------------------------------------|
	|					Networking				|
	 -------------------------------------------
	
	Virtualization is a technology that allows you to create multiple simulated environments or dedicated resources from a single, physical hardware system
	
	Containerization is the packaging together of software code with all its necessary components like libraries, frameworks, and other dependencies so that they are isolated in their own "container"
	
	The major differences are:
		
		In virtualization, the hypervisor creates an abstraction layer over hardware, so that multiple operating systems can run alongside each other.
		This technique is considered to be the first generation of cloud computing.

		Containerization is considered to be a lightweight version of virtualization, which virtualizes the operating system instead of hardware. Without the hypervisor, the containers enjoy faster resource provisioning. All the resources (including code, dependencies) that are needed to run the application or microservice are packaged together, so that the applications can run anywhere.
	
	
Page No: 44		How to avoid crawling duplicate URLs at Google scale?
	Option 1: Use a Set data structure to check if a URL already exists or not. Set is fast, but it is not space-efficient.
	Option 2: Store URLs in a database and check if a new URL is in the database. This can work but the load to the database will be very high.
	Option 3: Bloom filter. This option is preferred. Bloom filter was proposed by Burton Howard Bloom in 1970.
	It is a probabilistic data structure that is used to test whether an element is a member of a set.
		false: the element is definitely not in the set.
		true: the element is probably in the set.
	False-positive matches are possible, but false negatives are not.
	
Page No: 47		Why is a solid-state drive (SSD) fast?
	A solid state drive reads up to 10 times faster and writes up to 20 times faster than a hard disk drive.
	An SSD is a flash-memory based data storage device. Bits are stored into cells, which are made of floating-gate transistors. 
	SSDs are made entirely of electronic components, there are no moving or mechanical parts like in hard drives (HDD).

page No: 53		HTTP 1.0 -> HTTP 1.1 -> HTTP 2.0 -> HTTP 3.0 (QUIC).
	HTTP 1.0 was finalized and fully documented in 1996. Every request to the same server requires a separate TCP connection.
	HTTP 1.1 was published in 1997. A TCP connection can be left open for reuse (persistent connection), but it doesn’t solve the HOL (head-of-line) blocking issue.
	HOL blocking - when the number of allowed parallel requests in the browser is used up, subsequent requests need to wait for the former ones to complete.
	HTTP 2.0 was published in 2015. It addresses HOL issue through request multiplexing, which eliminates HOL blocking at the application layer, but HOL still exists at the transport (TCP) layer.
	HTTP 3.0 first draft was published in 2020. It is the proposed successor to HTTP 2.0. It uses QUIC instead of TCP for the underlying transport protocol, thus removing HOL blocking in the transport layer.
	
	QUIC is based on UDP. It introduces streams as first-class citizens at the transport layer.
	QUIC streams share the same QUIC connection, so no additional handshakes and slow starts are required to create new ones, but QUIC streams are delivered independently such that in most cases packet loss affecting one stream doesn't affect others.
	
	Question: When shall we upgrade to HTTP 3.0? Any pros & cons you can think of?
	
Page No: 55		How to scale a website to support millions of users?
	We will explain this step-by-step.
	The diagram below illustrates the evolution of a simplified eCommerce website. 
	It goes from a monolithic design on one single server, to a service-oriented/microservice architecture.

	Suppose we have two services: inventory service (handles product descriptions and inventory management) and user service (handles user information, registration, login, etc.).
	Step 1 - With the growth of the user base, one single application server cannot handle the traffic anymore. We put the application server and the database server into two separate servers.
	Step 2 - The business continues to grow, and a single application server is no longer enough. So we deploy a cluster of application servers.
	Step 3 - Now the incoming requests have to be routed to multiple application servers, how can we ensure each application server gets an even load? The load balancer handles this nicely.
	Step 4 - With the business continuing to grow, the database might become the bottleneck. To mitigate this, we separate reads and writes in a way that frequent read queries go to read replicas. 
			 With this setup, the throughput for the database writes can be greatly increased.
	
	Step 5 - Suppose the business continues to grow. One single database cannot handle the load on both the inventory table and user table. We have a few options:
		1. Vertical partition. Adding more power (CPU, RAM, etc.) to the database server. It has a hard limit.
		2. Horizontal partition by adding more database servers.
		3. Adding a caching layer to offload read requests.
	
	Step 6 - Now we can modularize the functions into different services. The architecture becomes service-oriented / microservice.
	
Page No: 58		DevOps Books
	Accelerate - presents both the findings and the science behind measuring software delivery performance.
	Continuous Delivery - introduces automated architecture management and data migration. It also pointed out key problems and optimal solutions in each area.
	Site Reliability Engineering - famous Google SRE book. It explains the whole life cycle of Google’s development, deployment, and monitoring, and how to manage the world’s biggest software systems.
	Effective DevOps - provides effective ways to improve team coordination.
	The Phoenix Project - a classic novel about effectiveness and communications. IT work is like manufacturing plant work, and a system must be established to streamline the workflow. Very interesting read!
	The DevOps Handbook - introduces product development, quality assurance, IT operations, and information security.
	What’s your favorite dev-ops book?
	
Page No: 60		Why is Kafka fast?
	Kafka achieves low latency message delivery through Sequential I/O and Zero Copy Principle.
	The same techniques are commonly used in many other messaging/streaming platforms.
	
Page No: 62		SOAP vs REST vs GraphQL vs RPC.
	SOAP (Simple Object Access Protocol)		XML Only
	REST (Representational State Transfer)		XML, JSON, HTML, plain text
	GraphQL										JSON
	RPC (Remote Procedure Call)					JSON, XML, Protobuf, Thrift, FlatBuffers
	
Page No: 63		How do modern browsers work?
	Google published a series of articles about "Inside look at modern web browser". It's a great read.
	Links:
	https://developer.chrome.com/blog/inside-browser-part1/
	https://developer.chrome.com/blog/inside-browser-part2/
	https://developer.chrome.com/blog/inside-browser-part3/
	https://developer.chrome.com/blog/inside-browser-part4/
	
Page No: 70		How to diagnose a mysterious process that’s taking too much CPU, memory, IO, etc?
	vmstat - reports information about processes, memory, paging, block IO, traps, and CPU activity.
	iostat - reports CPU and input/output statistics of the system.
	netstat - displays statistical data related to IP, TCP, UDP, and ICMP protocols.
	lsof - lists open files of the current system.
	pidstat - monitors the utilization of system resources by all or specified processes, including CPU, memory, device IO, task switching, threads, etc.
	
	The diagram below illustrates helpful tools in a Linux system.
	
=====================================
Linux Performance Observability Tools
=====================================

-----------------------------------------------------
|				Applications						|
|			----------------------------------------|
|			|		System Libraries				|
|---------------------------------------------------|
|				System Call Interface				|
|---------------------------------------------------|
|		VFS			|	Sockets		|				|
|------------------------------------	Scheduler	|
|	File Systems	|	TCP/UDP		|				|
|---------------------------------------------------|					
|	Volume Manager	|		IP		|	Virtual		|					-------------
|------------------------------------	Memory		|-------------------|	CPUs	|
|	Block Device	|	Net Device	|				|					-------------
----------------------------------------------------|						|
|					Device Drivers					|						|
-----------------------------------------------------					-------------
						|												|	DRAM	|
						|												-------------
				-----------------
				|	I/O Bridge	|
				-----------------
						|
						|
			-------------------------
			|						|
			|						|
	---------------------	-------------------------
	|	I/O controller	|	|	Network Controller	|
	---------------------	-------------------------
	|		|		|			|		|		|
	|		|		|			|		|		|
	Disk	Disk	Disk		Port	Port	Port
			
			
			
1.	Applications			->	perf , Ftrace , LTTng , BCC , bpftrace

2.	System Libraries		->	ltrace , gethostlatency

3.	System Call Interface	->	strace
	
4.1	VFS						->	opensnoop , lsof , fatrace , filelife , pcstat

4.2	File Systems			->	opensnoop , ext4dist , ext4slower , (& for btrfs , nfs , xfs , zfs)

4.3	Volume Manager			->	opensnoop , mdflush

4.4	Block Device			->	opensnoop , iostat , biosnoop , biolatency , biotop , blktrace


4.1	Sockets					->	ss

4.2	TCP/UDP					->	nstat , tcplife , tcpretrans , udpconnect

4.3	IP						-> 	nstat

4.4	Net Device				->	tcpdump


4.1	Scheduler				->	hardirqs , criticalstat , execsnoop , mpstat , profile , runqlen , offcputime , softirqs

4.2	Virtual Memory			->	hardirqs , criticalstat , vmstat , slabtop , free
	
	
5.	Device Drivers

6.	I/O Bridge

7.1	I/O Controller

7.2	Network Controller		->	nicstat , netstat , ip

8.1	Disk					->	SCSI log , swapon

8.2	Port					->	nicstat , netstat , ip , ethtool , snmpget , lldptool
			
			
		
CPUs						->	execsnoop , mpstat , profile , runqlen , offcputime , softirqs , turbostat , showboost , rdmsr

DRAM						->	numastat



Device Drivers -- I/O Bridge	->		perf , tiptop

Virtual Memory -- CPUs			->		top , atop , ps , pidstat

CPUs -- DRAM					->		tiptop , perf
				


Applications, System Libraries, System Call Interface, VFS, File Systems, Volume Manager	->	perf , Ftrace , LTTng , BCC , bpftrace

Block Device, Sockets, TCP/UDP, IP, Net Device, Scheduler, Virtual Memory, Device Drivers	->	perf , Ftrace , LTTng , BCC , bpftrace




		Page No: 76		Why is Redis so Fast?
		
			1.	RAM - based
			
					 -------- 
					|Register|					0.3ns
		  		   -------------
				  |	  L1 Cache	|				0.9ns
				 -----------------
				| 	L2 Cache 	  |				2.8ns
			   ---------------------
			  |		L3 Cache		|			12.9ns
			 -------------------------
			|			RAM			  |			120ns		-->	Redis uses RAM, not disk
		   -----------------------------
		  |				SSD				|		50-150us
		 ---------------------------------
		|				HDD				  |		1-10ms
		 ---------------------------------
				
			2.	IO Multiplexing & Single-threaded read/write
			
			
			Socket			IO Multiplex (multi-threaded)
			------			-----------------------------
			Socket1	----> Socket1
			
			Socket2 ----> Socket2 ----> Event Loop (single-threaded) ----> Task Queue ----> Event Dispatcher ----> Event Processors
			
			Socket3 ----> Socket3
			
			
			
			3.	Efficient Data Structure	
		
			
			1. Redis is a RAM-based database. RAM access is at least 1000 times faster than random disk access.
			2. Redis leverages IO multiplexing and single-threaded execution loop for execution efficiency.
			3. Redis leverages several efficient lower-level data structures.
			
			Question: Another popular in-memory store is Memcached. Do you know the differences between Redis and Memcached?
			You might have noticed the style of this diagram is different from my previous posts. Please let me know which one you prefer.


		Page No: 77		SWIFT payment network
			
			You probably heard about SWIFT. What is SWIFT? What role does it play in cross-border payments? You can find answers to those questions in this post.
			
			SWIFT for cross-border payments
			
			The Society for Worldwide Interbank Financial Telecommunication (SWIFT) is the main secure messaging system that links the world’s banks.
			
			The Belgium-based system is run by its member banks and handles millions of payment messages per day.
			The diagram below illustrates how payment messages are transmitted from Bank A (in New York) to Bank B (in London).
			
			Step 1: Bank A sends a message with transfer details to Regional Processor A in New York. The destination is Bank B.
			
			Step 2: Regional processor validates the format and sends it to Slice Processor A.
			The Regional Processor is responsible for input message validation and output message queuing. The Slice Processor is responsible for storing and routing messages safely.
			
			Step 3: Slice Processor A stores the message.
			
			Step 4: Slice Processor A informs Regional Processor A the message is stored.
			
			Step 5: Regional Processor A sends ACK/NAK to Bank A. ACK means a message will be sent to Bank B.
			NAK means the message will NOT be sent to Bank B.

			Step 6: Slice Processor A sends the message to Regional Processor B in London.
			
			Step 7: Regional Processor B stores the message temporarily.
			
			Step 8: Regional Processor B assigns a unique ID MON (Message Output Number) to the message and sends it to Slice Processor B
			
			Step 9: Slice Processor B validates MON.
			
			Step 10: Slice Processor B authorizes Regional Processor B to send the message to Bank B.
			
			Step 11: Regional Processor B sends the message to Bank B.
			
			Step 12: Bank B receives the message and stores it.
			
			Step 13: Bank B sends UAK/UNK to Regional Processor B. UAK (user positive acknowledgment) means Bank B received the message without error; 
			UNK (user negative acknowledgment) means Bank B received checksum failure.
			
			Step 14: Regional Processor B creates a report based on Bank B’s response, and sends it to Slice Processor B.
			
			Step 15: Slice Processor B stores the report.
			
			Step 16 - 17: Slice Processor B sends a copy of the report to Slice Processor A. Slice Processor A stores the report.
			
		
		Page No: 84		CDN (content delivery network)
			
			A content delivery network (CDN) refers to a geographically distributed servers (also called edge servers) which provide fast delivery of static and dynamic content.
			.
			.
			Over to you: How do you prevent videos cached on CDN from being pirated?
		
		Page No: 89		Foreign exchange in payment
			
			Have you wondered what happens under the hood when you pay with USD online and the seller from Europe receives EUR (euro)?
			This process is called foreign exchange.		
		
			Suppose Bob (the buyer) needs to pay 100 USD to Alice (the seller), and Alice can only receive EUR. The diagram below illustrates the process.
			1. Bob sends 100 USD via a third-party payment provider. In our example, it is Paypal. The money is transferred from Bob’s bank account (Bank B) to Paypal’s account in Bank P1.
			2. Paypal needs to convert USD to EUR. It leverages the foreign exchange provider (Bank E). Paypal sends 100 USD to its USD account in Bank E.
			3. 100 USD is sold to Bank E’s funding pool.
			4. Bank E’s funding pool provides 88 EUR in exchange for 100 USD. The money is put into Paypal’s EUR account in Bank E.
			5. Paypal’s EUR account in Bank P2 receives 88 EUR.
			6. 88 EUR is paid to Alice’s EUR account in Bank A.
		
			Now let’s take a close look at the foreign exchange (forex) market. It has 3 layers:
			
			Retail market. Funding pools are parts of the retail market. To improve efficiency, Paypal usually buys a certain amount of foreign currencies in advance.
			
			Wholesale market. The wholesale business is composed of investment banks, commercial banks, and foreign exchange providers. It usually handles accumulated orders from the retail market.
			
			Top-level participants. They are multinational commercial banks that hold a large number of certificates of deposit from different countries. They exchange these certificates for foreign exchange trading.
			
			When Bank E’s funding pool needs more EUR, it goes upward to the wholesale market to sell USD and buy EUR. When the wholesale market accumulates enough orders, it goes upward to top-level participants. Steps 3.1-3.3 and 4.1-4.3 explain how it works.
		

		Page No: 94		Block storage, file storage and object storage


 ---------------------------
|		Block Storage		|
 ---------------------------
|	 -----	 -----	 -----	|
|	|block|	|block|	|block|	|
|	 -----	 -----	 -----	|
|	 -----	 -----	 -----	|
|	|block|	|block|	|block|	|
|	 -----	 -----	 -----	|
|	 -----	 -----	 -----	|
|	|block|	|block|	|block|	|
|	 -----	 -----	 -----	|
|	 -----	 -----	 -----	|
|	|block|	|block|	|block|	|
|	 -----	 -----	 -----	|
 ---------------------------
 
 -------------------------------
| 		  File Storage			|
 -------------------------------
|	 							|
|	 /\--						|
|	|	 |						|
|	 ----						|
|	  |		 /\--		 --		|
|	  |---> |	 | ---> | -|	|
|	  |		 ----	|	 --		|
|	  |				|  			|
|	  |				|	/\--	|
|	  |				 ->|	|	|
|	  |					----	|
|	  |							|
|	  |		 /\--				|
|	  |---> |	 |				|
|	  |		 ----				|
|	  |							|
|	  |		 --					|
|	  |---> | -|				|
|	  |		 --					|
|	  |							|
|	  |		 --					|
|	   ---> | -|				|
|			 --					|
|								|
 -------------------------------

# tree
.
|-- bin -> usr/bin
|-- boot
|-- dev
|   |-- cachefiles
|   |-- console
|   |-- core -> /proc/kcore
|   |-- cpu
|   |   |-- 0
|   |   |   |-- cpuid
|   |   |   `-- msr
|   |   `-- 1
|   |       |-- cpuid
|   |       `-- msr
|   |-- cpu_dma_latency
|   |-- cuse
|   |-- fd -> /proc/self/fd
|   |-- full


 -----------------------------------
| 		  Object Storage			|
 -----------------------------------
|	 --				---------		|
|	|ID|		   | Metadata|		|
|	 --\		  / ---------		|
|		\--------/					|
|		| Object |		 --------	|
|		 /-------		|Metadata|	|
|		/				 --------	|
|  --------	  --------		|		|
| | Payload| | Payload|		|		|
|  --------	  --------\		|		|
|					   \ --------	|
|						| Object |	|
|						/--------	|
|					 --/			|
|					|ID|			|
|					 --				|
 -----------------------------------		
			
			
			Storage systems fall into three broad categories:
			
			Block storage	->	Good for Virtual machines (VM), high-performance applications like database
			File storage 	->	Good for General-purpose file system access
			Object storage	->	Good for Binary data, unstructured data
			
			Block storage
			
				Block storage came first, in the 1960s. Common storage devices like hard disk drives (HDD) and solid-state drives (SSD) that are physically attached to servers are all considered as block storage.
				
				Block storage presents the raw blocks to the server as a volume. This is the most flexible and versatile form of storage. 
				The server can format the raw blocks and use them as a file system, or it can hand control of those blocks to an application. 
				Some applications like a database or a virtual machine engine manage these blocks directly in order to squeeze every drop of performance out of them.
				
				Block storage is not limited to physically attached storage. Block storage could be connected to a server over a high-speed network or over industry-standard connectivity protocols like Fibre Channel (FC) and iSCSI.
				Conceptually, the network-attached block storage still presents raw blocks. To the servers, it works the same as physically attached block storage. 
				Whether to a network or physically attached, block storage is fully owned by a single server. It is not a shared resource.
	
			File storage
				
				File storage is built on top of block storage. It provides a higher-level abstraction to make it easier to handle files and directories.
				Data is stored as files under a hierarchical directory structure. File storage is the most common general-purpose storage solution.
				File storage could be made accessible by a large number of servers using common file-level network protocols like SMB/CIFS and NFS.
				The servers accessing file storage do not need to deal with the complexity of managing the blocks, formatting volume, etc.
				The simplicity of file storage makes it a great solution for sharing a large number of files and folders within an organization.

				https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tree_(command)
					In computing, tree is a recursive directory listing command or program that produces a depth-indented listing of files.
	
			Object storage
				
				Object storage is new. It makes a very deliberate tradeoff to sacrifice performance for high durability, vast scale, and low cost. 
				It targets relatively “cold” data and is mainly used for archival and backup. Object storage stores all data as objects in a flat structure. 
				There is no hierarchical directory structure. Data access is normally provided via a RESTful API. It is relatively slow compared to other storage types. 
				Most public cloud service providers have an object storage offering, such as AWS S3, Google block storage, and Azure blob storage.
	
	
		Page No: 97		Domain Name System (DNS) lookup
			
			DNS acts as an address book. It translates human-readable domain names (google.com) to machine-readable IP addresses (142.251.46.238).
			
			To achieve better scalability, the DNS servers are organized in a hierarchical tree structure.
			
			There are 3 basic levels of DNS servers:
			
			1. Root name server (.). It stores the IP addresses of Top Level Domain (TLD) name servers. There are 13 logical root name servers globally.
			2. TLD name server. It stores the IP addresses of authoritative name servers. There are several types of TLD names. For example, generic TLD (.com, .org), country code TLD (.us), test TLD (.test).
			3. Authoritative name server. It provides actual answers to the DNS query. You can register authoritative name servers with domain name registrar such as GoDaddy, Namecheap, etc.

			The diagram below illustrates how DNS lookup works under the hood:
			
			How does DNS resolve IP (Diagram is in https://blog.bytebytego.com/p/free-system-design-pdf-158-pages PDF)
			
			1. google.com is typed into the browser, and the browser sends the domain name to the DNS resolver.
			2. The resolver queries a DNS root name server.
			3. The root server responds to the resolver with the address of a TLD DNS server. In this case, it is .com.
			4. The resolver then makes a request to the .com TLD.
			5. The TLD server responds with the IP address of the domain’s name server, google.com (authoritative name server).
			6. The DNS resolver sends a query to the domain’s nameserver.
			7. The IP address for google.com is then returned to the resolver from the nameserver.
			8. The DNS resolver responds to the web browser with the IP address (142.251.46.238) of the domain requested initially.

			DNS lookups on average take between 20-120 milliseconds to complete (according to YSlow).
			
			
			DNS Explained (6 Mins)
			======================
			https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=72snZctFFtA
			
			
		Page No: 99		What happens when you type a URL into your browser?
			
			The diagram below illustrates the steps.
			
			(Diagram is in https://blog.bytebytego.com/p/free-system-design-pdf-158-pages PDF)
			
			URL Components
			--------------
				http://example.com/product/electric/phone
			
			1. Bob enters a URL into the browser and hits Enter. In this example, the URL is composed of 4 parts:
				scheme - https://. This tells the browser to send a connection to the server using HTTPS (port 443).
				domain - example.com. This is the domain name of the site.
				path - product/electric. It is the path on the server to the requested resource: phone.
				resource - phone. It is the name of the resource Bob wants to visit.
				
			2. The browser looks up the IP address for the domain with a domain name system (DNS) lookup. 
			   To make the lookup process fast, data is cached at different layers: browser cache, OS cache, local network cache and ISP cache.
			
			2.1 If the IP address cannot be found at any of the caches, the browser goes to DNS servers to do a recursive DNS lookup until the IP address is found (this will be covered in another post).
			
			3. Now that we have the IP address of the server, the browser establishes a TCP connection with the server.
			
			4. The browser sends a HTTP request to the server. The request looks like this:
				
				GET /phone HTTP/1.1
				Host: example.com
				
			5. The server processes the request and sends back the response. For a successful response (the status code is 200). 
			   The HTML response might look like this:
			   
				HTTP/1/1 200 OK
				Date: Sun, 30 Jan 2022 00:01:01 GMT
				Server: Apache
				Content-Type: text/html; charset=utf-8
				
				<!DOCTYPE html>
				<html lang="en">
				Hello world
				</html>
				
			6. The browser renders the HTML content.
			
		
		Page No: 113		Map rendering
			
			Google Maps Continued. Let’s take a look at 𝐌𝐚𝐩 𝐑𝐞𝐧𝐝𝐞𝐫𝐢𝐧𝐠 in this post.
			
			Pre-Computed Tiles
			------------------
			One foundational concept in map rendering is tiling. Instead of rendering the entire map as one large custom image, the world is broken up into smaller tiles.
			The client only downloads the relevant tiles for the area the user is in and stitches them together like a mosaic for display.
			The tiles are pre-computed at different zoom levels. Google Maps uses 21 zoom levels.
		
			For example, at zoom level 0, The entire map is represented by a single tile of size 256 * 256 pixels. Then at zoom level 1, the number of map tiles doubles in both north-south and east-west directions, while each tile stays at 256 * 256 pixels. So we have 4 tiles at zoom level 1, and the whole image of zoom level 1 is 512 * 512 pixels. With each increment, the entire set of tiles has 4x as many pixels as the previous level. The increased pixel count provides an increasing level of detail to the user.
			
			This allows the client to render the map at the best granularities depending on the client’s zoom level without consuming excessive bandwidth to download tiles with too much detail. This is especially important when we are loading the images from mobile clients.
			
			Road Segments
			-------------
			Now that we have transformed massive maps into tiles, we also need to define a data structure for the roads. We divide the world of roads into small blocks. We call these blocks road segments. Each road segment contains multiple roads, junctions, and other metadata.
			
			We group nearby segments into super segments. This process can be applied repeatedly to meet the level of coverage required.
			
			We then transform the road segments into a data structure that the navigation algorithms can use. The typical approach is to convert the map into a 𝒈𝒓𝒂𝒑𝒉, where the nodes are road segments, and two nodes are connected if the corresponding road segments are reachable
			neighbors. In this way, finding a path between two locations becomes a shortest-path problem, where we can leverage Dijkstra or A* algorithms.



Pre-Computed Tiles
------------------

Zoom Level 0
 --------  <---
|		 |	   |
|		 |	  256 px
|		 |	   |
 --------  <---


	Zoom Level 1
 -------- --------	<---
|		 |		  |		|
|		 |		  |		|
|		 |		  |		|
 -------- --------	   512 px
|		 |		  |		|
|		 |		  |		|
|		 |		  |		|
 -------- -------- 	<--- 



			Zoom Level 2
 -------- -------- -------- --------  <---
|		 |		  |		   |		|	  |
|		 |		  |		   |		|	  |	
|		 |		  |		   |		|	  |
 -------- -------- -------- --------	  |
|		 |		  |		   |		|	  |
|		 |		  |		   |		|	  |
|		 |		  |		   |		|	  |
 -------- -------- --------	--------	1024 px
|		 |		  |		   |		|	  |
|		 |		  |		   |		|	  |	
|		 |		  |		   |		|	  |
 -------- -------- -------- --------	  |
|		 |		  |		   |		|	  |
|		 |		  |		   |		|	  |
|		 |		  |		   |		|	  |
 -------- -------- --------	--------  <---





		
		Page No: 115		Interview Question: Design Google Maps
		
			Google started project Google Maps in 2005. As of March 2021, Google Maps had one billion daily active users, 99% coverage of the world in 200 countries.
			
			Although Google Maps is a very complex system, we can break it down into 3 high-level components. 
			In this post, let’s take a look at how to design a simplified Google Maps.
			
			
						Mobile User ----------> CDN ----------> Static Map Images (Object Storage)
							|
							|
						Load Balancer
							|
							|
			 -------------------------------
			|								|
	Navigation Service				Location Service
			|								|
	 ----------------						|
	|				 |						|
Geocoding DB	Road Segment DB		User Location DB


			Location Service
			----------------
			The location service is responsible for recording a user’s location update. The Google Map clients send location updates every few seconds. The user location data is used in many cases:
			- detect new and recently closed roads
			- improve the accuracy of the map over time 
			- used as an input for live traffic data.
			
			Map Rendering
			-------------
			The world’s map is projected into a huge 2D map image. It is broken down into small image blocks called "tiles" (see below).
			The tiles are static. They don’t change very often. An efficient way to serve static tile files is with a CDN backed by cloud storage like S3.
			The users can load the necessary tiles to compose a map from nearby CDN.
			
			What if a user is zooming and panning the map viewpoint on the client to explore their surroundings?
			
			 -------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
			|	An efficient way is to pre-calculate the map blocks with different zoom levels and load the images when needed.	|
			 -------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
			
			Navigation Service
			------------------
			This component is responsible for finding a reasonably fast route from point A to point B. It calls two services to help with the path calculation:
			
			1.	Geocoding Service: resolve the given address to a latitude/longitude pair
			2.	Route Planner Service: this service does three things in sequence:
				- Calculate the top-K shortest paths between A and B
				- Calculate the estimation of time for each path based on current traffic and historical data
				- Rank the paths by time predictions and user filtering. For example, the user doesn’t want to avoid tolls.
				
		Page No: 119	Money movement
			
			One picture is worth more than a thousand words. This is what happens when you buy a product using Paypal/bank card under the hood.
			
			To understand this, we need to digest two concepts: clearing & settlement.
			
			Clearing is a process that calculates who should pay whom with how much money; 
			while settlement is a process where real money moves between reserves in the settlement bank.
			
			Let’s say Bob wants to buy an SDI book from Claire’s shop on Amazon.
			
			- Pay-in flow (Bob pays Amazon money):
				1.1 Bob buys a book on Amazon using Paypal.
				1.2 Amazon issues a money transfer request to Paypal.
				1.3 Since the payment token of Bob’s debit card is stored in Paypal, Paypal can transfer money, on Bob’s behalf, to Amazon’s bank account in Bank A.
				1.4 Both Bank A and Bank B send transaction statements to the clearing institution. It reduces the transactions that need to be settled. Let’s assume Bank A owns Bank B $100 and Bank B owns bank A $500 at the end of the day. When they settle, the net position is that Bank B pays Bank A $400.
				1.5 & 1.6 The clearing institution sends clearing and settlement information to the settlement bank. Both Bank A and Bank B have pre-deposited funds in the settlement bank as money reserves, so actual money movement happens between two reserve accounts in the settlement bank.
			
			- Pay-out flow (Amazon pays the money to the seller: Claire):
				2.1 Amazon informs the seller (Claire) that she will get paid soon.
				2.2 Amazon issues a money transfer request from its own bank (Bank A) to the seller bank (bank C). Here both banks record the transactions, but no real money is moved.
				2.3 Both Bank A and Bank C send transaction statements to the clearing institution.
				2.4 & 2.5 The clearing institution sends clearing and settlement information to the settlement bank. Money is transferred from Bank A’s reserve to Bank C’s reserve.

			Notice that we have three layers:
				- Transaction layer: where the online purchases happen
				- Payment and clearing layer: where the payment instructions and transaction netting happen
				- Settlement layer: where the actual money movement happen
			
			The first two layers are called information flow, and the settlement layer is called fund flow.
			
			You can see the information flow and fund flow are separated. In the info flow, the money seems to be deducted from one bank account and added to another bank account, but the actual money movement happens in the settlement bank at the end of the day.
			
			Because of the asynchronous nature of the info flow and the fund flow, reconciliation is very important for data consistency in the systems along with the flow.
			
			It makes things even more interesting when Bob wants to buy a book in the Indian market, where Bob pays USD but the seller can only receive INR.
			

		Page No: 122	Reconciliation
			
			My previous post about painful payment reconciliation problems sparked lots of interesting discussions.
			One of the readers shared more problems we may face when working with intermediary payment processors in the trenches and a potential solution:
		
		
			1. Foreign Currency Problem: 	
				When you operate a store globally, you will come across this problem quite frequently.
				To go back to the example from Paypal - if the transaction happens in a currency different from the standard currency of Paypal, this will create another layer, where the transaction is first received in that currency and exchanged to whatever currency your Paypal is using.
				There needs to be a reliable way to reconcile that currency exchange transaction.
				It certainly does not help that every payment provider handles this differently.

			2. Payment providers are only that - intermediaries. 
				Each purchase does not trigger two events for a company, but actually at least 4.
				The purchase via Paypal (where both the time and the currency dimension can come into play) trigger the debit/credit pair for the transaction 
				and then, usually a few days later, another pair when the money is transferred from Paypal to a bank account (where there might be yet another 
				FX discrepancy to reconcile if, for example, the initial purchase was in JPY, Paypal is set up in USD and your bank account is in EUR).
				There needs to be a way to reconcile all of these.
				
			3. Some problems also pop up on the buyer side that is very platform-specific. 
				One example is shadow transaction from Paypal: if you buy two items on Paypal with 1 week of time between the two transactions, Paypal will first debit money from your bank account for transaction A.
				If at the time of transaction B, transaction A has not gone through completely or is canceled, there might be a world where Paypal will use the money from transaction A to partially pay for transaction B, 
				which leads to only a partial amount of transaction B being withdrawn from the bank account.

			In practice, this usually looks something like this:
				1) Your shop assigns an order number to the purchase
				2) The order number is carried over to the payment provider
				3) The payment provider creates another internal ID, which is carried over across transactions within the system
				4) The payment ID is used when you get the payout on your bank account (or the payment provider bundles individual payments, which can be reconciled within the payment provider system)
				5) Ideally, your payment provider and your shop have an integration/API with the tool you use to (hopefully automatically) create invoices. This usually carries over the order id from the shop (closing the loop) and sometimes even the payment id to match it with the invoice id, which you then can use to reconcile it with your accounts receivable/payable. :)
			
			
			Credit: A knowledgeable reader who prefers to stay private. Thank you!
			
			
		Page No: 131	Reconciliation
		
			Reconciliation might be the most painful process in a payment system. 
			It is the process of comparing records in different systems to make sure the amounts match each other.
			
			For example, if you pay $200 to buy a watch with Paypal:
			- The eCommerce website should have a record about the purchase order of $200.
			- There should be a transaction record of $200 in Paypal (marked with 2 in the diagram).
			- The Ledger should record a debit of $200 dollars for the buyer, and a credit of $200 for the seller. This is called double-entry bookkeeping (see the table below).	
			
			Let’s take a look at some pain points and how we can address them:
			
			Problem 1: Data normalization. When comparing records in different systems, they come in different formats. For example, the timestamp can be "2022/01/01" in one system and "Jan 1, 2022" in another.
			
			Possible Solution: we can add a layer to transform different formats into the same format.
			
			Problem 2: Massive data volume
			
			Possible Solution: we can use big data processing techniques to speed up data comparisons. If we need near real-time reconciliation, a streaming platform such as Flink is used; otherwise, end-of-day batch processing such as Hadoop is enough.
			
			Problem 3: Cut-off time issue. For example, if we choose 00:00:00 as the daily cut-off time, one record is stamped with 23:59:55 in the internal system, but might be stamped 00:00:30 in the external system (Paypal), which is the next day.
				In this case, we couldn’t find this record in today's Paypal records. It causes a discrepancy.

			Possible Solution: we need to categorize this break as a "temporary break" and run it later against the next day's Paypal records.
				If we find a match in the next day's Paypal records, the break is cleared, and no more action is needed.
			
				You may argue that if we have exactly-once semantics in the system, there shouldn’t be any discrepancies.
				But the truth is, there are so many places that can go wrong.
				Having a reconciliation system is always necessary. It is like having a safety net to keep you sleeping well at night.
			
		
		Page No: 136	Avoid double charge
			
			One of the most serious problems a payment system can have is to double charge a customer. 
			When we design the payment system, it is important to guarantee that the payment system executes a payment order exactly-once.
			

 -------------------------------------------------------------------
|															RETRY	|
|		 --------					 ----------------				|
|		| Client |					| Payment System |				|
|		 --------					 ----------------				|
|			|								|						|
|			|								|						|
|			|---------- Pay $10 ----------->|						|
|			|								|						|
|			|<-------------X----------------| Payment failed		|
|			|								|						|
|			|								|						|
|			|---------- Pay $10 ----------->|						|
|	Retry	|								|						|
|			|<-------------X----------------| Payment failed		|
|			|								|						|
|			|								|						|
|			|---------- Pay $10 ----------->|						|
|	Retry	|								|						|
|			|<-------------X----------------| Payment failed		|
|			|								|						|
|			|								|						|
|			|---------- Pay $10 ----------->|						|
|	Retry	|				 /				|						|
|			|<-------------\/---------------| Payment succeeded		|
|																	|
 -------------------------------------------------------------------


 -------------------------------------------------------------------------------
|															IDEMPOTENCY			|
|																				|
|	 -----------------------------------------------------------------------	|
|	|																	 	|	|
|	|	 --------					 				   ----------------	 	|	|
|	|	|		 |-- POST {idempotency-key: UUID} --> |				   |	|	|
|	|	| Client |									  | Payment System |	|	|
|	|	|		 |<------- Charge succeeded ----------|				   |	|	|
|	|	 --------					 				   ----------------		|	|
|	|																		|	|
|	 -----------------------------------------------------------------------	|
|										 ||										|
|										 ||										|
|									   	-  -									|
|									   	\  /									|
|										 \/										|
|	 -----------------------------------------------------------------------	|
|	|																	 	|	|
|	|	 --------					 				   ----------------	 	|	|
|	|	|		 |-- POST {idempotency-key: UUID} --> |				   |	|	|
|	|	| Client |									  | Payment System |	|	|
|	|	|		 |<----- Return previous message -----|				   |	|	|
|	|	 --------					 				   ----------------		|	|
|	|	  Retry									Server has already seen the	|	|
|	|											idempotency key. Do not		|	|
|	|											process the request again.	|	|
|	 -----------------------------------------------------------------------	|
|																				|
 -------------------------------------------------------------------------------
	
		At the first glance, exactly-once delivery seems very hard to tackle, 
		but if we divide the problem into two parts, 
		it is much easier to solve. Mathematically, an operation is executed exactly-once if:
		
		1.	It is executed at least once.
		2.	At the same time, it is executed at most once.
		
		We now explain how to implement at least once using retry and at most once using idempotency check.
		
		RETRY
			Occasionally, we need to retry a payment transaction due to network errors or timeout.
			Retry provides the at-least-once guarantee. For example, as shown in Figure 1,
			the client tries to make a $10 payment, but the payment keeps failing due to a poor network connection. 
			Considering the network condition might get better, 
			the client retries the request and this payment finally succeeds at the fourth attempt.	
		
		IDEMPOTENCY
			From an API standpoint, idempotency means clients can make the same call 
			repeatedly and produce the same result.
		
			For communication between clients (web and mobile applications) and servers, 
			an idempotency key is usually a unique value that is generated by clients and expires after a certain period of time.
			A UUID is commonly used as an idempotency key and it is recommended by many tech companies such as Stripe and PayPal.
			To perform an idempotent payment request, an idempotency key is added to the HTTP header: <idempotency-key: key_value>.


		Page No: 138	Payment security
			
			A few weeks ago, I posted the high-level design for the payment system.
			Today, I’ll continue the discussion and focus on payment security.
			
			The table below summarizes techniques that are commonly used in payment security.
			If you have any questions or I missed anything, please leave a comment.

 -----------------------------------------------------------------------------------
|			Problem				|			Solution								|
|-------------------------------|---------------------------------------------------|
| Request/Response				| Use HTTPS											|
| eavesdropping					|													|
|-------------------------------|---------------------------------------------------|
| Data tampering				| Enforce encryption and integrity monitoring		|	
|								|													|
|-------------------------------|---------------------------------------------------|
| Man-in-the-middle attack		| Use SSL and authentication certificates			|
|								|													|
|-------------------------------|---------------------------------------------------|
| Data loss						| Database replication across multiple regions		|	
|								| and take snapshot of data							|
|-------------------------------|---------------------------------------------------|
| Distributed denial-of-service	| Rate limiting and firewall						|
|								|													|
|-------------------------------|---------------------------------------------------|
| Card theft					| Tokenization. Instead of using real card			|
|								| numbers, tokens are stored and used for payment	|
|-------------------------------|---------------------------------------------------|
| PCI compliance				| PCI DSS is an information security standard for	|
|								| organizations that handle branded credit cards	|
|-------------------------------|---------------------------------------------------|
| Fraud							| Address verification, Card Verification Value		|
|								| (CVV), user behaviour analysis etc				|
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------------------


		Page No: 142	Quadtree
			
			In this post, let’s explore another data structure to find nearby restaurants on Yelp or Google Maps.
			
			A quadtree is a DATA STRUCTURE that is commonly used to partition a TWO-DIMENSIONAL space 
			by RECURSIVELY subdividing it into FOUR QUADRANTS (GRIDS)
			until the contents of the GRIDS meet certain criteria (see the first diagram).
			
			QUADTREE
			
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
|																		|
|					Dividing an area into a quadtree					|
|																		|
|	 ---------------		 ---------------		 ---------------	|
|	|				|		|		|		|		|		|10m|11m|	|
|	|				|		|NW(40m)|NE(30m)|		|		|---|---|	|
|	|				|		|		|		|		|		|4m |5m |	|
|	|	  200m		|------>|-------|-------|------>|-------|-------|	|
|	|				|		|		|		|		|		|		|	|
|	|				|		|SW(70m)|SE(60m)|		|		|		|	|
|	|				|		|		|		|		|		|		|	|
|	 ---------------		 --------------- 		 ---------------	|
|																		|
|																		|
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
 									||
 									||
 									||
 									||
 									\/
 ---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
|																						|
|		Building a quadtree						 ---									|
|											200m|	|									|
|												 ---									|
|												  |										|
|												  |										|
|							   -----------------------------------						|
|							nw|			ne|			sw|			se|						|
|							 ---		 ---		 ---		 ---					|
|							|40m|		|30m|		|70m|		|60m|					|
|							 ---		 ---		 ---		 ---					|
|										  |												|
|										  |												|
|					   -----------------------------------								|
|					nw|			ne|			sw|			se|								|
|					 ---		 ---		 ---		 ---							|
|					|12m|		|4m |		|5m |		|9m |							|
|					 ---		 ---		 ---		 ---							|
|								  |														|
|								  |														|
|				 ---------------------------------										|
|			  |			  |			  |			  |										|
|			 ---		 ---		 ---		 ---									|
|			|	|		|	|	 340|	|		|	|									|
|			 ---		 ---		 ---		 ---									|
|									  |													|
|									  |													|
|	 				   -----------------------------------								|
|					  |			  |			  |			  |								|
|					 ---		 ---		 ---		 ---							|
|					|50	|		|90	|	 	|60	|		|140|							|
|					 ---		 ---		 ---		 ---							|
|														  |								|
|														  |								|
|													 ----------- 						|
|													|			|						|
|												   ---		   ---						|
|												  |60 |		  |80 |						|
|												   ---		   ---			 			|
|																						|
 ---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------

			Quadtree is an IN-MEMORY DATA STRUCTURE and 
			it is not a DATABASE SOLUTION.
			It runs on each LBS(Location-Based Service, see last week’s post) SERVER, 
			and the DATA STRUCTURE is built at SERVER START-UP time.
			
			The second diagram explains the quadtree building process in more detail.
			The ROOT NODE represents the WHOLE WORLD MAP.
			The ROOT NODE is recursively broken down into 4 QUADRANTS 
			until NO NODES are left with more than 100 businesses.
			
			How to get nearby business with quadtree?
				- 	Build the quadtree in MEMORY.
				-	After the quadtree is built, 
					start searching from the ROOT and traverse the tree, 
					until we find the LEAF NODE where the search origin is.
				-	If that LEAF NODE has 100 businesses, 
					return the NODE. 
					Otherwise, add businesses from its neighbors until enough businesses are returned.	
				
			Update LBS Server and rebuild quadtree
				-	It may take a FEW MINUTES to build a quadtree in MEMORY 
					with 200 MILLION BUSINESSES at the SERVER START-UP TIME.
				-	WHILE THE QUADTREE IS BEING BUILT, THE SERVER CANNOT SERVE TRAFFIC.
				-	Therefore, we should roll out a new release of the SERVER incrementally 
					to A SMALL SUBSET of SERVERS at a time. 
					This AVOIDS taking a large SWATHE of the SERVER CLUSTER OFFLINE and causes service brownout.
			

		Page No: 144	How do we find nearby restaurants on Yelp?
			
			Here are some design details behind the scenes.
			
			There are two key services (see the diagram below):
			
					
								Proximity Service Design
					
											 ()
											-||-
											 /\ 
											 
											 ||
											 ||
											 \/
										 ---------------
										| Load balancer |
										 ---------------
												|
												|
										 -----------------
										|				  |
								/search/nearby		/businesses/{:id}
										|				  |
										\/				  \/
								 ---------------	 -----------
								| Local Based	|	| Business	|
								| Service		|	| Service	|
								 ---------------	 -----------
								 |		|	|			  |
			   ------------------	  Read	|			Write
			  |							|	|			  |
	 ---------|-------------------------|---|-------------|-------------------------
	|		  |							|	|			  |							|
	|		Read					---- 	 --Read--	   ---------------			|
	|		  |					   |				 |					  |			|
	|		  \/				   \/ 				 \/					  \/		|
	|	 -----------		 -----------		 -----------		 -----------	|
	|	|-----------|		|-----------|		|-----------|		|-----------|	|
	|	|			|		|			|		|			|		|			|	|
	|	| Replica	|		| Replica	|		| Replica	|		| Primary	|	|
	|	|			|		|			|		|			|		|			|	|
	|	 -----------		 -----------		 -----------		 -----------	|
	|		 /\					 /\					  /\			  |	|	|		|
	|		 |					 |					  |	Replicate	  |	|	|		|
	|		 |					 |	Replicate		   ---------------	|	|		|
	|		 |	Replicate		  --------------------------------------	|		|
	|		  --------------------------------------------------------------		|
	|							Database Cluster									|
	 -------------------------------------------------------------------------------







				 ---------------
				|		|		|
			--->| 	01	| 	11	|
		   |	|		|		|
		   |	|----------------
		   |	|		|		|
		   |	| 	00	| 	10	|
		   |	|		|		|
		   |	 ---------------
		   |
		   |
		   |
		   |_------------------
		  	|					|
			|					\/
			|	 -------------------------------
			|	|		|		|		|		|
			|	| 0101	| 0111	| 1101	| 1111	|
			|	|		|		|		|		|
			|	|-------------------------------|
			|	|		|		|		|		|
			|	| 0100	| 0110	| 1100	| 1110	|
			|	|		|		|		|		|
			 -->|-------------------------------|
				|		|		|		|		|
				| 0001	| 0011	| 1001	| 1011	|
				|		|		|		|		|
				|-------------------------------|	 
				|		|		|		|		|
				| 0000	| 0010	| 1000	| 1010	|
				|		|		|		|		|
				 -------------------------------
		
		
		
			-	Business Service
				-	Add/delete/update restaurant information
				-	Customer view restaurant details
				
			-	Local-based Service (LBS)
				-	Given a radius and location, return a list of nearby restaurants
		
			How are the restaurant locations stored in the database 
			so that LBS can return nearby restaurants efficiently?
			
			Store the latitude and longitude of restaurants in the database? 
			The query will be very inefficient when you need to calculate the distance between you and every restaurant.
		
			One way to speed up the search is using the GEOHASH ALGORITHM.
		
			First, divide the PLANET into FOUR QUADRANTS along with the PRIME MERIDIAN and EQUATOR:
			
			-	Latitude range [-90, 0] is represented by 0
			-	Latitude range [0, 90] is represented by 1
			-	Longitude range [-180, 0] is represented by 0
			-	Longitude range [0, 180] is represented by 1

			Second, divide each grid into four smaller grids.
			Each grid can be represented by alternating between longitude bit and latitude bit.
		
			So when you want to search for the nearby restaurants in the red-highlighted block, you can write SQL like:
			
			SELECT * FROM geohash_index WHERE geohash LIKE '01%'
			
			Geohash has some limitations. 
			There can be a lot of restaurants in one block (downtown New York), but none in another block (ocean).
			So there are other more complicated algorithms to optimize the process.
			Let me know if you are interested in the details.
		
		
		
		
		Page No: 147	How does a modern stock exchange achieve microsecond latency?
		
			The principal is:
			
			Do less on the critical path !
			
			- Fewer tasks on the critical path
			- Less time on each task
			- Fewer network hops
			- Less disk usage

										 ---------------------------------------
										|	Low Latency Stock Exchange Design	|
										 ---------------------------------------

 -------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
|												SINGLE PHYSICAL SERVER												|
|																													|
|		 ---------------------------		 ---------------------------		 ---------------------------		|
|		|		Order Manager		|		|		Matching Engine		|		|	Market Data Publisher	|		|
|		|							|		|							|		|							|		|
|		|	 --------------------	|		|	 --------------------	|		|	 --------------------	|		|
|		|	| | | | |			 |	|		|	| | | | |			 |	|		|	| | | | |			 |	|		|
|		|	| | | | |		.....|	|		|	| | | | |		.....|	|		|	| | | | |		.....|	|		|
|		|	| | | | |			 |	|		|	| | | | |			 |	|		|	| | | | |			 |	|		|
|		|	 --------------------	|		|	 --------------------	|		|	 --------------------	|		|
|		|	  Application Loop		|		|	  Application Loop		|		|	  Application Loop		|		|
|		 ---------------------------		 ---------------------------		 ---------------------------		|
|					/\										/\								/\						|
|					||										||								||						|
|					\/										\/								\/						|
|		 ---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------		|
|		|																									|		|
|		|											MMap													|		|
|		|																									|		|
|		 ---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------		|
|				/\						/\						/\						/\							|
|				||						||						||						||							|
|				\/						\/						\/						\/							|
|		 ---------------		 ---------------		 ---------------		 ---------------					|
|		|				|		|				|		|	Aggregated	|		|	Position	|					|
|		|	Reporter	|		|	Logging		|		|	Risk Check	|		|	Keeper		|					|
|		|				|		|				|		|				|		|				|					|
|		 ---------------		 ---------------		 ---------------		 ---------------					|
|																													|
 -------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------


	  ===========================================================================================================
	||																											||
	||	For the stock exchange, the critical path is:															||
	||		- START: an order comes into the order manager														||
	||		- mandatory risk checks																				||
	||		- the order gets matched and the execution is sent back 											||
	||		- END:	the execution comes out of the order manager												||
	||																											||	
	||	Other non-critical tasks should be removed from the critical path. 										||
	||	We put together a design as shown in the diagram:														||
	||																											||
	||	-	deploy all the components in a SINGLE GIANT SERVER (NO CONTAINERS)									||
	||																											||	
	||	-	use SHARED MEMORY as an EVENT BUS to communicate among the COMPONENTS, NO HARD DISK					||
	||																											||	
	||	- 	KEY COMPONENTS like Order Manager and Matching Engine are SINGLE-THREADED on the CRITICAL PATH,		||
	||		and each pinned to a CPU so that there is NO CONTEXT SWITCH and NO LOCKS							||
	||																											||
	||	- 	the SINGLE-THREADED APPLICATION loop executes tasks one by one in SEQUENCE							||
	||																											||	
	||	- 	other COMPONENTS listen on the EVENT BUS and react accordingly										||
	||																											||
	  ==========================================================================================================



		Page No: 147	Match buy and sell orders
			
			Stocks go up and down. Do you know what data structure is used to efficiently match buy and sell orders?
			
			
			
								PRICE		QUANTITY
									
									 		 -----------
				depth of ask	100.13		| 100 | 200 |<------------------ price levels
											|-----------|
								100.12		| 600 | 900 |
											|-----------|-----
								100.11		| 900 | 700 | 400 |
											|-----------------------
Sell book		best ask		100.10		| 200 | 400 | 1100| 100 |
											 -----------------------


											 -----------------
Buy book		best bid		100.08		| 500 | 600 | 900 |
											|-----------------
								100.07		| 100 | 700 |
											|-----------------------
								100.06		| 1100| 400 | 300 | 200 |
											|-----------------------
				depth of bid	100.05		| 500 | 100 |
											 -----------

			Buy 2700 shares: 2700 - 200 - 400 - 1100 - 100 - 900 = 0



			Stock exchanges use the data structure called ORDER BOOKS.
			
			An ORDER BOOK is an electronic list of buy and sell orders, organized by price levels.
			
			It has a buy book and a sell book, where each side of the book contains a bunch of price levels,
			and each price level contains a list of orders (first in first out).

			The image is an example of price levels and the queued quantity in each price level.
			
			So what happens when you place a market order to buy 2700 shares in the diagram?


			-	The buy order is matched with all the sell onrders at price 100.10, and the first order at price 100.11 (illustrated in light red).

			-	Now because of the big buy order which “eats up” the first price level on the sell book, the best ask price goes up from 100.10 to 100.11.
			
			-	So when the market is bullish, people tend to buy stocks, and the price goes up and up.


			An efficient data structure for an order book must satisfy:
			
			-	Constant lookup time. Operations include: get volume at a price level or between price levels, query best bid/ask.
			
			-	Fast add/cancel/execute/update operations, preferably O(1) time complexity. Operations include: place a new order, cancel an order, and match an order.			
			



		Page No: 151	Stock exchange design
			
			The stock market has been volatile recently.
			
			Coincidentally, we just finished a new chapter "Design a stock exchange".
			I will use plain English to explain what happens when you place a stock buying order.
			The focus is on the exchange side.
			

													 ============================
													||	STOCK EXCHANGE DESIGN	||
													 ============================

									  ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------
									 |																					|
									 |		STOCK EXCHANGE																|
									 |																					|
									 |							candlestick chart, order book							|
									 |		  ------------------------------------------------------------				|
									 |		 |															  |				|
									 |		 |			   ------------									  |				|
									 |		 |			  | Aggregated |							 ------------		|
									 |		 \/			  |	  Risk	   |							|  Market	 |		|
									 |	 ---------		  |	  Check	   |							|	Data	 |		|
						12			 |	|  Data	  |		   ------------								|  Publisher |		|
		   --------------------------|->| Service |				/\									 ------------		|
		  |							 |	|		  |				|										  /\			|
		  |							 |	 ---------				|4										11|				|
	 -----------					 |							\/										  \/			|
	|			|					 |					   -------------							 -------------		|
	|	 ----	|					 |					  |	   Order	|							|  Matching	  |		|
	|	|	 |	|					 |					  |	  Manager	|							|  Engine	  |		|
	|	 ----	|  1	 --------	2|	  --------	 3	  |				|	6	 -----------		|			  |		|
	|	  /\	|------>|		 |---|-->| Client |------>|  --------	|------>|			|------>|  --------	  |		|
	|			|		| Broker |	 |	 | Gateway|		  | | Wallet |	|		| Sequencer |		| | Order  |  |		|
	|	 ---	|<------|		 |<--|---| 		  |<------|  --------	|<------|			|<------| | Book   |  |		|
	|	| - |	|  10	 --------	9|	  --------	 8	  |				|		 -----------	7	|  --------	  |		|
	|	|	|	|			e.g.	 |					  |				|							|			  |		|
	|	| - |	|		Robinhood	 |					   -------------							 -------------		|
	|	 ---	|	  MorganStanley	 |							|														|
	|			|					 |							\/														|
	 -----------					 |					   -------------												|
									 |					  |				|												|
									 |					  |  Reporter	|												|
									 |					  |				|												|
									 |					   -------------												|
									 |							|														|
									 |							\/														|
									 |						 -----------												|
									 |						|-----------|												|
									 |						|			|												|
									 |						|	DB		|												|
									 |						|			|												|
									 |						 -----------												|
									 |						orders, trades												|
									 |																					|
									  ----------------------------------------------------------------------------------


			Step 1: client places an order via the broker’s web or mobile app.
			
			Step 2: broker sends the order to the exchange.
			
			Step 3: the exchange client gateway performs operations such as validation, rate limiting, authentication, normalization, etc, and sends the order to the order manager.

			Step 4: the order manager performs risk checks based on rules set by the risk manager.
			
			Step 5: once risk checks pass, the order manager checks if there is enough balance in the wallet.
			
			Step 6-7: 	the order is sent to the matching engine. The matching engine sends back the execution result if a match is found. 
						Both order and execution results need to be sequenced first in the sequencer so that matching determinism is guaranteed.
						
			Step 8 - 10: execution result is passed all the way back to the client.
			
			Step 11-12: market data (including the candlestick chart and order book) are sent to the data service for consolidation. 
						Brokers query the data service to get the market data.
						
			Step 13: 	the reporter composes all the necessary reporting fields (e.g. client_id, price, quantity, order_type, filled_quantity, remaining_quantity) 
						and writes the data to the database for persistence

			
			A stock exchange requires extremely low latency.
			While most web applications are ok with hundreds of milliseconds latency, 
			a stock exchange requires micro-second level latency.
			I’ll leave the latency discussion for a separate post since the post is already long.
			


		Page No: 153	Design a payment system
		
			Today is Cyber Monday.
			Here is how money moves when you click the Buy button on Amazon or any of your favorite shopping websites.

			I posted the same diagram last week for an overview and a few people asked me about the detailed steps, so here you go:


							 ()
							-||-												|
							 /\ 												|
							 													|
							 ||													|
					1. Payment Event	 										|
							 ||													|
							 ||													|		 -----------		 ------------
	 ------------------------||------------------------------------------		|		|			|		|			 |
	|						 \/											|		|		|	Paypal	|		|	VISA	 |
	|	 -------		   ---------					----------		|		|		|			|		|			 |
	|	|-------| <--2.---| Payment |---3. Payment---> | Payment  |-------5. ---------->|	Stripe	|------>| MasterCard |
	|	|		|		  | Service |	   Order	   | Executor |		|		|		|			|		|			 |
	|	 -------		   ---------					----------		|		|		|	adyen	|		|			 |
	|						 |   |							/\			|		|		 -----------		 -----------
	|				   ------     -----						||4.		|		|			Payment 			Card
	|				  |8.			   |6.					\/			|		|			Service				Schemes
	|			  --------			--------			  -------		|		|			Providers
	|			 | Ledger |		   | Wallet |			 |-------|		|		|			(PSP)
	|			  --------		 	--------			 |		 |		|		|
	|				  |					|				  -------		|		|
	|				  9.				7.								|		|
	|				  |					|								|		|
	|				  \/				\/								|		|
	|				-------			  -------							|		|
	|			   |-------|		 |-------| 							|		|
	|			   |	   |		 |		 |		Payment System		|		|
	|				-------			  -------							|		|
	|																	|		|
	 -------------------------------------------------------------------		|
																		Inside	|	Outside


			1.	When a user clicks the "Buy" button, a payment event is generated and sent to the payment service.
			2.	The payment service stores the payment event in the database.
			3.	Sometimes a single payment event may contain several payment orders. For example, you may select products from multiple sellers in a single checkout process.
				The payment service will call the payment executor for each payment order.
			4.	The payment executor stores the payment order in the database.
			5.	The payment executor calls an external PSP to finish the credit card payment.
			6.	After the payment executor has successfully executed the payment, the payment service will update the wallet to record how much money a given seller has.
			7.	The wallet server stores the updated balance information in the database.
			8.	After the wallet service has successfully updated the seller’s balance information, the payment service will call the ledger to update it.
			9.	The ledger service appends the new ledger information to the database.
			10.	Every night the PSP or banks send settlement files to their clients.
				The settlement file contains the balance of the bank account, together with all the transactions that took place on this bank account during the day.


		Page No: 155	Design a flash sale system
			
			Black Friday is coming. Designing a system with extremely high concurrency, high availability 
			and quick responsiveness needs to consider many aspects ALL THE WAY FROM FRONTEND TO BACKEND.
			
			See the below picture for details:
			
			
										 -----------------------------------
										| PRODUCT DESIGN					|
										| - use reCaptcha before placing	|
										| an order to prevent bots (for		|
										| suspicious activities)			|
										 -----------------------------------

														 -------------------------------
									 -----------		| FRONTEND DESIGN				|
				 ()					|			|		| - less web page elements		|
				-||- -------------> |			|		| - less JavaScript loading		|
 				 /\ 				|			|		| - static contents in CDN		|
									 -----------		 -------------------------------
										 | |
									   =======
										  |
										  |
										  \/			 -----------
									   --------  		|			|
									  |-|---|--|------->|	CDN		|
									  |----|---|		|			|
									   --------		 	 -----------
										  |
										  |
										  \/
									 -----------		 --------------		 -------------------------------
									| 			|		|			   |	| RATE LIMIT					|
									|	NGINX	|------>| Risk Control |	| - anti-DDoS					|
									| 			|		|			   |	| - suspicious IPs banned		|
									 -----------		 --------------		| - rate limit on a single IP	|
										  |									 -------------------------------
										  |
										  |
										  |
										  |
										  |
										  |
 -------------------------------		  \/							 -------------------------------	
| OVER SALE PREVENTION			|	 -----------						| BACKEND SERVICE DESIGN		|	
| - lock the inventory when 	|	|			|						| - isolated instance for Black	|	
| 	placing an order.			|	|	Service	|---------------		| 	Friday						|	
|	Decrease the inventory after|	|			|				|		| - Use MESSAGE QUEUE for		|	
|	the payment is successful	|	 -----------				|		|	ASYNCHRONOUS processing		|	
 -------------------------------								|		| - less RPC, less dependencies |	
										  |						|		|	on other services			|	
										  |						|		| - no Single Point of failure	|
										  |						|		 -------------------------------	
 -------------------------------		  |						|
| DATA STORAGE 					|		  |						|
| - isolated cache for Black	|		  |						|
| 	Friday						|		  \/					\/
| - Inventory is maintained in	|	 -----------			 -----------
|	the cache					|	|			|			|-----------|
| - Database is updated separate|	| Cache		|			|	DB	|
|	in batch					|	|			|			|			|
 -------------------------------	 -----------			 -----------




			Design Principles
				1.	Less is more - less element on the web page, fewer data
					queries to the database, fewer web requests, fewer system
					dependencies
					
				2.	Short critical path - fewer hops among services or merge into
					one service
				
				3.	Async - use message queues to handle high TPS (Transaction Per Second )
				
				4.	Isolation 
					-	isolate STATIC and DYNAMIC contents, 
					-	isolate PROCESSES and DATABASE for rare items
					
				5.	Overselling is bad. When Decreasing the inventory is important
				
				6.	User experience is important.
					We definitely don’t want to inform users that they have successfully placed orders but later tell them no items are actually available


			Page No: 157	Back-of-the-envelope estimation
				
				Recently, a few engineers asked me whether we really need back-of-the-envelope estimation in a system design interview.
				I think it would be helpful to clarify.
				
				Estimations are important because we need them to understand the scale of the system and justify the design.
				It helps answer questions like:

				-	Do we really need a distributed solution?
				-	Is a cache layer necessary?
				-	Shall we choose data replication or sharding?
				
				Here is an example of how the estimations shape the design decision.
				
				One interview question is to design proximity service and how to scale geospatial index is a key part of it.\
				Here are a few paragraphs we wrote to show why jumping to a sharding design without estimations is a bad idea:

				One common mistake about scaling the geospatial index is to quickly jump to a sharding scheme without considering the actual data size of the table.
				In our case, the full dataset for the geospatial index table is not large (quadtree index only takes 1.71G memory and storage requirement for geohash index is similar).
				The whole geospatial index can easily fit in the working set of a modern database server.
				However, depending on the read volume, a single database server might not have enough CPU or network bandwidth to service all read requests.
				If that is the case, it will be necessary to spread the read load among multiple database servers.

				There are two general approaches to spread the load of a relational database server.
				We can add read replicas or shard the database.

				Many engineers like to talk about sharding during interviews.
				However, it might not be a good fit for the geohash table.
				Sharding is complicated. The sharding logic has to be added to the application layer.
				Sometimes, sharding is the only option. In this case though, since everything can fit in the working set of a database server,
				there is no strong technical reason to shard the data among multiple servers.
				
				A better approach, in this case, is to have a series of read replicas to help with the read load. 
				This method is much simpler to develop and maintain. Thus, we recommend scaling the geospatial index table through replicas.


